『Thank you, my twilight』— the Pillows
世界必須先被毀滅 之後才能變得美麗
The world must be destroyed before it can become beautiful.
Life, Life is beautiful
生命，生命如此美麗
這是我在心中描繪的世界的願景
This is the world I envisioned.
僕のルーレット　回り続けてる
我的輪盤 會一直轉動下去
這是世界應有的樣子
This is how the world should be.
但在這個世界裡
But in this world,
只有我的身體在腐爛
only my body is rotting --
She, She is wonderful
她，她是這般美妙
漸漸朽壞
becoming decayed.
沒錯 它正在朽壞
Yes, decaying.
その瞳に今を映したい
想要讓她的眼睛 映照出現在
也許這是我原本該有的樣貌
Maybe this is how my body should have been.
也許這才是真正的我
Maybe this is my true self.
迷わないでもぎ取った予感を
毫不猶豫抓住的預感
但我最後還是想起
But then finally, I remember
誰かと待ち合わせてるみたいに
好像在等待著誰似的
我還只是一個國中生
that I'm still only a junior high student,
我並沒思考過什麼
that I wasn't thinking about anything,
見えたなら間違いじゃない
如果看到就肯定不會有錯
還有 這裡從不曾發生什麼事了不起的事情
and that nothing amazing has ever happened here.
一切都是那麼平凡
Everything is ordinary.
キミを待ってたんだ
一直在等你
She, She is wonderful
她，她是這般美妙
その瞳に今を映したい
想要讓她的眼睛 映照出現在
迷わないでもぎ取った予感を
毫不猶豫抓住的預感
奇跡は起こらなくても充分だぜ
就算不發生奇蹟也足夠了
今日が最後の日でも
就算今天是最後一天也好
Thank you, my twilight
謝謝你 我的晨曦
鬧鐘
重　啟
本字幕由 SweetSub 製作　僅做交流學習之用途
翻校：ピロピラ ピロコ　其它：tastySugar
停下！
Hold it right there!
要我說多少次呢？
How many times do I have to repeat myself?
在下樓之前 先要說“早安”
Before you come downstairs, you got to say, "Good morning".
好吧 再來一次
Okay, why don't we give it another go?
三 二 …
Three, two...
酷美 親愛的 你的傲嬌人格每天都在進步
Hidomi, sweetie, you're getting better at that tsundere personality of yours everyday.
你這樣子我可以理解
I get that it's a thing you're doing,
但我是你的母親
but I am your mother,
不管怎樣 你還是要對我說“早安”
so you still have to at least say "good morning" to me.
早餐想吃什麼？
What would you like to eat?
我可以在你的早餐裡放一點本週的特色菜
I can add some of this week's special to your usual breakfast.
看到了嗎？炒納豆
See? Sautéed natto.
我不想吃早餐
I don't want any.
好吧 那路上小心
'Kay. Then you have a good day.
嗯
Hmm.
在你走之前 ——三 二…
But before you leave -- three, two...
早安 媽媽
Good morning...Mommy.
-早安！ -嗯
Morning! Mm-hmm.
早安，酷美！
Good morning, Hidomi!
嗯…早安
Mm-hmm...Morning.
“你只是這麼挑逗 當然什麼也不會出來啊”
"Ch'yeah, well, of course nothing's gonna come out if you keep teasing it like that."
她知道但還是繼續纏繞 轉動 迴旋
And she knew that and kept swirling and twirling and whirling
我宛如在天堂一般
and I was in heaven for eternity, infinity,
不要可憐我
no need to pity me
喂 他沒問題吧
Hey, you think he's feeling all right?
井出 你就明白說昨天到底發生什麼事了吧
Ide, would you just tell us what happened yesterday already?
哦吼吼 你是問我昨天嗎？
Oh-ho-ho -- yesterday, you ask?
那個老師昨天在你家過夜的吧
That teacher spend the night at your place, right?
告訴我們到底怎樣了
You better tell us what happened.
有些事情需要留下想像的空間
You guys, some things ought to be left to the imagination.
真的假的
For reals?! Seriously?
天啊 恭喜恭喜
No, way. Oh, my gosh. Congratulations.
那當然了
Well, yeah...
說真的嗎？
For reals?
還有 你昨天說的那個秘密計劃是什麼？
By the way, what was the secret plan you were talking about yesterday?
那個嘛？
Oh, that?
到底是什麼？
What's that?
藝術展覽門票
Art gallery tickets.
什麼 藝術？你逗我呢？
Wait, art? For reals?
這可是女人的弱點
Women are total suckers for these kinds of things,
懂不懂啊？
know what I'm saying, boys?
這種東西和你不太搭
This kind of thing doesn't really seem like you.
我用不著擅長這個 可是 當你看著藝術作品的時候
This doesn't have to be my thing. I mean, when you gaze upon art,
你就會情不自禁開始思考這個我們生活的世界甚至是宇宙
you can't help but reflect on the world we live in or the universe.
考察它 從縫隙裡窺視它
Like, scrutinize it, peek into it from a gap,
因為 你們懂的 我對那個
because you know me -- I'm interested in the --
怎麼說呢 哲學？很有興趣的
Aw, how do I put it? The...philosophical?
扯吧 你最討厭這些了
Since when? You hate that stuff.
這是真的！OK 好吧 你們說得對
That's not true! Okay, well, to be honest, you got me.
我不是真的喜歡藝術
I'm not really interested in fine art like this,
但是 想一想 我們兩個人能在一個美好的夜晚 一起看美好的東西
but check it -- If the two of us can go have a beautiful night out, looking at beautiful things,
然後 說不定我們的關係就能進一步發展呢？
then who knows? We might be able to deepen our relationship, ya know?
關係？天啊！
Relationship?! I don't believe it!
井出！
Ide!
快說！你打算什麼時候進一步發展
Now spill it! When are you making that decision
你們的關係？
about your relationship?!
-你說什麼呢？-當然是——！
W-W-W-What do you mean? You know what!
大人的約會
Your adult date.
噓 森 現在別說這個
Shush, Mori. Let's not talk about that right now.
不如我們來說說你今天的有趣時裝吧？
Why don't we talk about your interesting fashion choices today instead?
-嗯 有什麼問題嗎? - 你怎麼會穿著裙子？
Yeah, what about it? Well, what the heck are you doing wearing a skirt?
這是中性裝扮 現在時興這個
It's unisex, and it's in right now.
馬可 這是中性 沒錯吧？
You'd call this unisex, right, Marco?
嗯 對 中性
Huh? Yeah. Unisex.
中性？那是什麼？什麼？
Unisex? What is that? What?
你居然沒聽說過 你太過時了
I can't believe you've never heard of it. You are so out of touch.
如果你在時尚界 說出“社會性別”這個詞
If you breathe the word "gender" in the fashion world,
會被人丟到老人院
they'll throw you in a nursing home.
-什麼？真的？-當然是真的
Wait, for reals? I swear!
現在世界上的潮人都在穿裙子 你不知道嗎？
All the hippest guys are wearing skirts nowadays, don't ya know?
馬可 這是真的嗎？
Marco, is that true?
你的這個睡公園板凳的
Does this mean your old-fart buddies
老古董朋友突然就時尚起來了？
sleeping on park benches are suddenly fashionable?
你說誰老古董呢？
Who are you calling an old fart?!
呃 我不曉得
Well, I don't know.
人應該想穿什麼就穿什麼
People should be able to wear whatever.
說得對！我說得沒錯吧？
That's right! I'm right, see?
好好好 隨便你
Okay, fine. I really don't care.
但是能不能不要讓我看到你的內褲？
Will you just stop showing me your underwear?
我可沒有特地露出來給你看
It's not like I'm purposely flashing you.
-看的人是你 -但這在我的視野裡
You're the one who's looking. But it's in my view,
人眼會本能地去看出現在視野裡的內褲
and one's eye's are instinctively drawn to underwear in their sight.
馬可 我說的不對嗎？
Right, Marco?
I guess, yeah.
嗯 說的沒錯
我決不允許你看我的小褲褲
There's absolutely no reason for you to be looking at my panties.
這不是“小褲褲” 這是男用內褲
Don't call them "panties." They are briefs.
你明明隨時都可以對著島崎老師的小褲褲看到爽！
Since you can get an eyeful from Miss Shimazaki's panty buffet anytime you want!
■
B班（23）
YOU:  還沒有確定是否要參加賞花的
同學，今天截止哦
RYO: 我參加
St: 現在多少人了
YOU: 大約一半（·∞·）
Kaha: 你這什麼表情
YOU: 不確定人數隨便猜出結果的笑
Eri: 我參加 期待
Sophie: 我也參加 謝謝
Anna: 我去我去 我可以幫忙占位置
YOU:謝謝 也幫忙買東西哦
Sao: 那我占好位置之後也去幫忙
YOU: 好——
大家 跟著我說 早安
Good morning, everybody. Now repeat after me --
All: Good morning, everybody. Now repeat after me.
請坐
Sit down.
我們原本就坐著
We're already sitting.
棒極——了
Maaarvelous...
滿堂紅呀
A full house, then.
那就開始上課吧
Now then, to kick off today's class
我先提個問題吧
I would like to pose a question to all of you who are starting
即將開始合理又不幸的新的一天的少年少女們
an understandably regrettable day as members of the current youth.
對你們而言世上最重要的是什麼？
What in your estimation is the most important thing in the world to you?
B班（23）
St: 對對 現在還穿著學生服的 233
sao: 為什麼說是學生服呢？
St: 特地穿制服的男生也就只有他了
kaho: 真的嗎？其它沒了？
St: 真的啊 我來上課的時候特地看了
RYO: 你確定沒看錯？你只是瞟了一眼吧
St: 那個書包 肯定是他沒錯！
jinno: 書包啊笑 我被說服了
mh: 確實233
mh: 如果是真的這不就糟糕了嗎
sao: 太噁心了
kaho: 手呢
St: 不清楚
St: 我只看見了臉
■
對 就是你們 你們是社會上最弱的一環
Yes, you, who are the weakest links in our society.
對 就是你
Yes. You over there.
-我不知道 -回答正確
-I don't know. -Correct answer.
B班（23）
St: 島醬從破舊的公寓裡出來
St: 然後井出也出來了
sao: 島醬她幾歲了來著
kaho: 比他大多了吧
RYO: 她在井出家過夜了？
kaho: 處男畢業!?
St: （>m<）
mh: 哇
sao:  已經不會再繼承處男之志了233
jinno: “老師——！”他這麼叫的吧
kaho: “島醬——”什麼的吧233
YOU: 和老師搞在一起 真是太噁心了
sao: 不過“島醬”這個稱呼也很土嘛
正合適啦
■
對任何問題都沒有清晰的答案
Not having clear and distinct answers for any question
蠢動著自己動物般性慾獲得滿足
and feeling fulfilled by jerking your animalistic sexual urges --
青春期的你們只知道這樣的生活
that is the only life you know as youth
在我們眼裡你們就是這樣一無是處
with absolutely no skill to convince us otherwise.
我到任這個班級
It has been exactly one week to the day
到今天已經整整一個禮拜了
since I was assigned to teach this class,
我只想說…
and I just want to say...
所有你們需要知道的 我都已經教給你們了
I have taught you everything you need to know.
現在開始今天的授課
Now for today's lesson.
-求求你  -我們不該做這個
-Please. -We shouldn't be doing this.
-老師 我
-Oh, Teacher. Oh, ah.
-這是不對的  -老師
-This is so wrong. -Oh, Teacher. Oh.
-你真壞
-You're so bad.
-老師 我  -你會害我惹上麻煩的
-Teacher, I -- -You're gonna get me in trouble.
-我忍不住
-I can't help myself.
-看看你對我做的 -老師！
-Look what you're doing to me. -Teacher!
-老師！
-Oh, Teacher! Oh!
什麼鬼？她在給她看什麼？
The hell? What is she making her watch?
聽起來很糟糕 非常糟糕
Whatever it is it sounds naughty -- real naughty.
下一個
Next.
你怎麼一點點反應都沒有？
Would it kill you to have even the tiniest reaction to this?
你是想等到自己花都謝了再進入青春期嗎？
You don't want to wait until you're over the hill to hit adolescence, do you?
好吧 到此為止
Fine. I've seen all I need to.
-你們誰是下一個？-我！
Which one of you is next? I am!
呃 井出你用不著測試
Eh, I don't need to test you, Ide.
除了他還有誰？
Huh? Who's next besides him?
-我 我！-森 待會告訴我們你看了什麼
-Oh! Oh! Me! -Mori, tell us what you see!
恐怕不行 我聽說你必須自己看
I don't think I can. I hear you have to see for yourselves.
真無聊
-我試過了 -好噁心
What's the big deal?
-I tried! -Nasty!
是…是什麼？蔬菜
W-W-What is it? Vegetables.
嘿 公主小姐 可以給我一張餐巾嗎？
Hey, princess, could I get a napkin, please?
抱歉 我的酪梨帕菲好了嗎？
Sorry, but is my avocado parfait ready?
酷美醬 請幫我咖啡續杯
Hidomi-chan, more coffee, please?
她那種態度真是太棒了
She's at her best when she gives us attitude like that.
我就喜歡她用責罵的眼神俯視我
I just love it when she looks down on us with those judgy eyes.
同感
Same here.
你做得棒極了 公主小姐
You're on fire, princess.
你真的很有潛力
You have what it takes to be a champ, huh?
謝謝你來店裡幫我 酷美
Thanks for helping out, Hidomi, sweetie.
幫了大忙
It really needed it today.
唔
Mm.
不過
That said,
我真的應該抓緊考慮僱人了
I should probably look into hiring someone soon.
不能因為咖啡店的事情耽誤你的時間
We can't have you wasting your valuable time helping me out at the café.
這裡的工廠看起來和那一個一模一樣
The Plant here looks just like the other one.
發出的聲音也是一樣的
It makes the same sound, too.
他現在在哪呢
I wonder where he is right now.
我最近開始覺得
I've been thinking --
我們是不是不要再等他了
Maybe it's time we stopped waiting for him.
也許我們應該向前看
Maybe it's time for us to move on.
對不起 我不該說這些
I'm sorry. I shouldn't say things like this.
但是你——
But now you're --
媽媽 我——
Mommy, you know what?
嗯？
Huh?
酷美！
Hidomi!
剛才真是千鈞一髮呢 夫人
That was a close one, ma'am.
我向您道歉
My apologies.
要是再遲一點 她就要溢出了
A little bit more, and she would've overflowed.
溢出？
Overflowed?
奇怪了
That's strange.
-剛才的撞擊應該致命才對 -致命?!
-I was sure it was a fatal hit. -Fatal hit?!
很不幸 夫人
Unfortunately, ma'am...
您的女兒平安無事
your daughter is going to be fine.
很不幸？！
That's unfortunate?!
酷美 親愛的！
Hidomi, dear!
你還好嗎？受傷了沒有？
Are you okay? Are you hurt?
喂！那是我的！
Hey, that's mine!
沒有在放音樂
It's not even playing anything.
還給我！
Give it back!
這是哪裡來的？
Where did you get this?
這不是在大街上隨隨便便就能買到的東西
It's not something anyone can just walk off the street and buy.
-這是… -嗯？
-This is just... -Hmm?
這是有人送給我的
It was a gift.
你不應該戴著這個
I don't think you should wear them.
這個不適合你
They don't suit you.
假裝自己聽不見——
Pretending you can't hear --
你喜歡這樣 對嗎？
That's, like, your thing, am I right?
當你對這個世界按下了暫停鍵
When you hit pause on the world like that,
你的身體也會漸漸開始腐壞
your body will slowly start to rot away.
這是你所希望的嗎？
Is that what you want to happen to you?
請 請等一下！
Wait a minute! You there!
夫人 您的女兒沒有死
Just so you know, I take full responsibility
我會承擔全部責任的
for your daughter hanging on to her life.
對了 還有一件事…
Oh, and by the way...
當心騎著 Vespa 的女人
careful of the woman on the Vespa -- for your own good.
酷美！記下她的車牌號了嗎？
Hidomi! Her plates! Did you get them?
肇事逃逸！肇事逃逸！
Hit-and-run! Hit-and-run!
千萬不要變成這樣不負責任的大人！
Never be an irresponsible adult like that!
她是誰？她怎麼回事？
Who is she? What's with her?
不知道 但是她有點帥哦
I don't know, but you got to admit she sure was cool.
哎？
Heh...
我對自己毫無期待
There is nothing I want to be.
我什麼事情都不想做
There's nothing I want to do.
我甚至不知道自己想成為什麼樣子的人
I don't even have an image of what I want to be.
我什麼都沒有
I have nothing.
有的只是…無
All that exists...is zero.
那是什麼？
What is that?
酷美？親愛的？
Hidomi? Sweetie?
-媽媽！-酷美！
-Mom! Mama! -Hidomi!
雲雀…弄？呃 我…
Hiba...ji-jiri? Oh, I --
是你嗎 井出？
Is that you, I-I-Ide?
它開始行動了 但這是哪一個？
It's started to move, but which is it?
-那個是什麼鬼東西？-天曉得！
-What the heck is that thing? -I have no idea!
我在回家的路上 然後——
I was just walking home, and then --
-你這麼晚還在外面？-呃 我有事要做
-You were out this late? -Uh, I had stuff to do,
然後那個東西就突然出現了
and that thing just suddenly appeared.
好吧 但是從哪裡？
Yeah, but from where?
呃 好像是從我的腦袋裡出來的
Well, it was like from my head.
好像甩掉它了
I think we lost it.
可惡 到底怎麼回事？
Holy shit! What the hell's going on?!
別過來！
No!
我明白了 原來如此
I see now. That's how it is, huh?
喂！她人在哪？
Hey! Where is she --
把那個東西從你身體裡拉出來的傢伙？
the one who pulled that out of you?!
回答我！你被撞了吧？
Answer me! You were hit, weren't you?
是不是一個騎著 Vespa 的女人？
Was it a woman on a Vespa?
Ves...pa?
喂
Hey.
你是誰？井出他沒事吧？
Who are you? And Ide...is he okay?
我會儘量給他治療的
I'm going to do what I can for his wounds.
-你回家吧 -等一下
-You get home safe, okay? -Wait a minute.
順帶一提
Oh, by the way,
那個很適合你 讚
that thing looks good on you. Nice.
『Little Busters』— the Pillows
嚇死我了
Thank goodness.
你沒有受傷真是太好了
Well, I'm so glad nothing actually happened to you,
酷美 親愛的
Hidomi, dear.
嗯
Hmm.
媽媽可擔心了
You know, Mommy was so worried
以為你要離家出走呢
that maybe you decided to run away from home.
With the kids sing out the future
孩子們歌唱著未來
Maybe, kids don't need the masters
也許孩子們不需要主人
但是如果真的要離家出走
But if youwere going to run away,
一定要搞得轟轟烈烈哦
you should do it with a bang.
Just waiting for the little busters
只要等小混蛋們到來
但是千萬別把房子給砸了
Just please try not to break the house next time,
好嗎？-嗯
all right, sweetie. -Mm.
這——這是？
Bu-- But why?
她想要為昨天的事情負責
She's taking responsibility for yesterday.
自我介紹一下吧
Please introduce yourself.
我是仁由
I'm Jinyu.
我靠！那些繃帶是怎麼回事？
Whoa! What's with all those bandages?
你怎麼了井出？
Yeah, what happened to you, Ide?
不知道該怎麼跟你們說
Man, I don't even know where to start.
發生了很多 很多事…
A lot of stuff happened, quite a lot of stuff.
“很多事”？
"A lot of stuff"?
那算什麼？
What kind of answer is that?
這跟沒說有什麼區別
That's like a non-answer answer.
在你們開始合理又災難性的新的一天之前
Today, as you start on your understandably
時下的少年少女們
disastrous day as modern-day youth,
我作為現實生活中決定性的贏家
I, as someone who is the clear winner in life structurally,
要告訴你們很重要的事情
would like to present to you something very important --
關於如何在這個世界上生存
the "this and that" on how to live in this universe.
■
B班（23）
U.Beviaqua: 話說 Takeshi 是不是
喜歡 Emily？
KAs: 真的嗎？！
Akihiro: 真的是這樣嗎？！
St: 我都不知道！！
RYO: 現在已經 Free 了吧？
U.Beviaqua: 機會！！
KAs: 機——會！！
Akihiro: 加油！！
U.Beviaqua: 過了這個村就沒了這個店！
U.Beviaqua: 可不能放過這次機會
TK: 欸？
TK: 這是在說我嗎？
U.Beviaqua: 會去的吧
你們會被測試
You will be tested on it,
甚至每天的生活本身就是測試
insomuch as every day in itself is a test.
-對 就是你 - 呃…
-Yes. You over there. -Uh...
回答錯誤
Wrong answer.
■
B班（23）
U.Beviaqua: 反正 Free 了
TK: 蛤？
Akihiro: 是的 因為 Free 了
安東: Free!
TK: 喂 等等
U.Beviaqua: 你是不會做出不好好利用
Free 的那種沒勁事吧？
安東: 那麼——Take 醬怎麼做？
TK: 你們這些人
U.Beviaqua: 只能利用好 Free 了！
Akihiro: 好好利用吧！！
安東: 這樣美味的 Free 可是很難得的哦！
KAs: 同意
安東: Free 好啊，Free 真是好！
U.Beviaqua: Freefree 喔 Freefree
KAs: Furifuri
Akihiro: Furifuri?
安東: Furikuri?
我最近想明白了
I figured out something recently.
與其為了隨機的問題
Instead of preparing a concrete answer
準備具體的答案 我認為
to random questions, I have come to the conclusion
並不存在你們的生存之道
that there is no real way to live,
對於你們這些只要
not for those of you who exist contently
蠢動著動物般的性慾就能獲得滿足
by only jerking your animalistic sexual urges to fulfillment,
在我們眼裡一無是處的人
and you who have absolutely no skill to convince us otherwise.
我付出了那麼多 但是成果少得可憐
I gave so, so much, but there was very little output.
微不足道隻能供人玩樂的小蟲子對我毫無價值
I have no use for the tiny pieces of scum bugs that have been toyed with.
Furi…kuri…
Fooly...Cooly...
聽你們老師一言 我不希望你們成為不存在的孩子
Listen to your teacher. I have no desire for all of you to wind up as nonexistent youth.
我要讓你們都變成宇宙級別的大人
What I want is for all of you to become adults on a cosmological scale!
■
B班（23）
mi-: FuriKuri
ichiro-: furi Kuri
kanako: Furi Kuri！！？
daidai: FLCL
kome: FuriKuri
竹尾: furikuri
(^o^): FL--CL--
wa: FuriKuri
ASADA: f l c l！
oshiyama: Furi！Kuri！
sada: FLCLFLCLFLCL
KUBO: Furi Kuri！
kiyo: Furi Kuri！！
arai: FLCL！！
（FLCL的假名和英文洗刷版）
你不需要翅膀也能在宇宙探險
You don't need wings to go venture out into the universe.
誰會需要長翅膀的四輪汽車？
Who would ride a four-wheeled car with wings, anyway?
你們不可以變成那樣的大人
You must not become that kind of adult.
明白了嗎？你們不需要四個輪子！
Do you understand me? You do not need four wheels!
你們只需要兩個——就像池塘裡的底棲魚一樣
You only need two -- like a bottom-feeding fish in a pond,
在低垂的柳樹下面聚成一群
gathering underneath a weeping willow tree.
Furi Kuri 和 FLCL 的洗刷版
你們的下方有強大的重力
There's a lot of gravity underneath all of you...
...so stand up! Be as adequate as you can, a complete mess,
所以站起來！你們就越差強人意越好 最好變成一團糟
生來注定平庸！
born to be mild!
這就對了 我想要的終於要出現了
That's right, the real one's finally appearing.